Several days have passed since
the end of the culture festival.
文化祭が終わって数日
The ardent atmosphere that had been
prevalent throughout the school
学校の中を漂っていたあの熱っぽい空気は
has now completely grown cold.
今やすっかり冷めていた
Moreover...
そして…
...the bitterness of the chill
was growing worse.
寒さは厳しさを増していた
We need to hurry and get
our Cubs ready for winter.
カブの冬支度　早くしないと
You're right. There's no telling
how much that will cost.
そうね… いくらかかるかわからないし
For now, I should be thrifty.
当分節約かぁ
Me, too.
私も
What do you have?
そっちは？
Coffee.
コーヒー
Well, it has been a good while
since I made it.
いれてからだいぶ時間がたってるからね
They say coffee tastes different
depending on who made it.
コーヒーの味は　いれる人間で変わるって
So what's in yours?
こっちは？
Barley tea.
麦茶
Tastes a lot like coffee substitute.
代用コーヒーみたいな味ね
I'm trying to go without vending
machine coffee for a while.
しばらく自販機のコーヒーも我慢かな
Same here.
同じく
I asked someone in class where you were,
クラスの子に聞いたけど　本当にここで食べてるんですね
and you really do eat lunch
down here, huh?
Mm-hmm. What brings you down?
うん　どうしたの？こんなとこまで
Well, our shop just put in an espresso
machine for our café space.
あの…
うちの店のカフェスペースに　エスプレッソマシンを置いたんです
I wanted to treat you two, so if you'd
like, please come by sometime.
それでご馳走したいので
よかったらお店に来てください
My papa said he wanted to thank you for
what you did during the culture festival.
パパも 2 人に文化祭のお礼を言いたいって
How does today sound?
今日でもいいのかな？
"Super Cub Episode 8"
"Shii's Place"
I'd be delighted!
喜んで！
"Super Cub Episode 8"
"Shii's Place"
初めての小さな旅路
目的地ならいらないよ
何もない私の頬に
手招きするように風が吹く
寄り道　回り道
いつもの景色も鮮やかに
右手をひねるたび　何度でも胸が弾むから
さあ　ギアを上げて　顔を上げて
どこまでも伸びてく道だって
昨日より少し遠くまで
きみとなら怖くない　どこだって
私ひとりでは　作れない風だ
Sorry to keep you.
お待たせしました
Wow, that's an Alex Moulton, isn't it?
へぇ　アレックス・モールトンじゃない
It has a truss frame with
a rubber cone suspension.
トラスフレームにラバーコーンサス
日本製モールトンじゃなくて　イギリスの AM シリーズ　お城製ってやつね
That isn't a Japanese-made Moulton,
that's the British AM series.
A "Castlebuilt," right?
Papa insisted that I have this one,
but I've rather come to like it.
パパに押しつけられるようにもらったんだけど
結構気に入ってて
Want me to pull you along
until we get to your place?
家まで引っ張ってってあげようか
Huh?
I've seen people go merrily right
into a ditch while doing that.
それをやって　2 人仲よく溝に落ちたヤツを見たことがある
I-I'll just go on ahead.
さ　先に行くから
Please follow me.
ついてきてください！
This is it. This is my shop, "Beurre."
ここです　ここが私のお店　「ブール」です！
It means "butter" in French.
フランス語でバターって意味なんですよ
This place is the only one around
that makes decent German bread.
この辺でちゃんとしたドイツ風のパンを作ってるのは　この店だけなのよ
The name is French,
but the bread is German?
名前はフランス語で　パンはドイツ風？
And at the culture festival,
she was a barista at an Italian bar.
文化祭ではイタリアンバールでバリスタ
Call them transnational,
I guess--or scattershot.
無国籍というか　無節操
Thanks for waiting. Come on in.
お待たせしました！
どうぞ
I'm home!
ただいま～
What is this? It's like
there's no cohesiveness.
なんだろう　なんだかまとまりが…
A British sandwich stand and American
diner inside a Tyrolean-style building.
チロル風の建物の中は
イギリスのサンドイッチスタンドとアメリカンダイナー
Like I said, transnational
and scattershot.
言ったでしょ　無国籍で無節操だって
あれが？
Is that it?
Yes. It's a used one,
はい　中古ですけど
but after using the one at the culture
festival, I just had to have one.
文化祭で使ってみたら　どうしても欲しくなっちゃって
I bought it with my savings.
貯金で買ったんです
Hey, Reiko-san. Welcome.
やぁ　礼子さん
いらっしゃい
Hello.
どうも
Is that girl Koguma-san?
あの子が小熊さんかい？
Mm-hmm.
うん
Thank you so much for coming over.
ようこそお越しくださいました
My daughter told me all about
the café at the culture festival
娘から文化祭のカフェでのお話を聞いて
一度お会いしたいと思っていました
and I was hoping I could meet you.
We're here to enjoy
some free coffee today.
今日はタダでコーヒーを飲みにきたんですけど
Yes, by all means, enjoy some of
the coffee I'm so proud of.
えぇ　ぜひ私の自慢のコーヒーをご馳走させてください
娘はおいしいと言ってくれないんですがね
My daughter can't bring herself
to tell me it's any good, though.
I'm going to let Reiko-chan and
Koguma-san have my coffee.
礼子ちゃんと小熊さんには私のコーヒーを飲んでもらいます
Papa, we don't want your American coffee.
パパのアメリカンコーヒーはいりませ～ん
We'll take both, please.
両方ください
Reiko and I can take one
of each and then share.
私と礼子で　別のをもらってシェアすればいい
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
Thanks for waiting.
お待たせしました
This is a medium roast Hawaiian Kona.
ハワイアン・コナのミディアムローストです
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
Here, Reiko-chan.
One dark roast Kalosi Toraja.
はい　礼子ちゃん
カロシトラジャの深煎り
Thanks.
ありがとう
Oh... Enjoy yourselves.
ゆっくりしてってね
Welcome!
いらっしゃいませ～
Well, if you'll excuse me...
それじゃ　失礼します
It really is different from
what I make at home.
やっぱうちでいれるのとは違う！
It's a little bitter...
but still delicious.
少し苦い
でも　おいしい
Among bikers, good cafés are essential.
バイク乗りの間じゃ　カフェっていうのは必須でね
So much so that the expression
"café racer" exists.
カフェレーサーって言葉があるくらいなの
The coffee and tea you drink
in these cafés keeps you warm
カフェのコーヒーやお茶は　飲む暖房で疲労回復薬であり　興奮剤ってこと
and acts as a stimulant
to replenish your energy.
Mm-hmm...
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございました！
こんな所で店を開いて　商売になるんですか？
Are you actually able to run a business
opening a shop out here?
I got my fill of "business"
working at a company in Tokyo.
商売は東京で会社勤めしていたときに十分したから
If I can make a living baking my favorite
bread for the summer cottagers,
夏の別荘客を相手に　好きなパンを焼いて暮らせれば
それでいいと思ってたんですが…
I figured that would be all I needed...
...but apparently, it's still not
enough to let me settle down.
どうやらまだ楽はさせてくれないみたいです
That's why you should hurry up
and let me take over the business.
だからパパは早く私に店を譲ってくれればいいの
マズ～い黒パンなんてやめて
We can quit baking your nasty rye bread
and start selling paninis
and bruschettas instead!
パニーニとブルスケッタを売るんだから
イタリア野郎にパンの焼き方や味わい方がわかるかってんだ
You think those Italian clowns know
anything about baking or savoring bread?
I know that people who want to
have yummy food and enjoy life
おいしいものを食べて人生を楽しみたい人は　ドイツのパンなんて食べませんよ～
don't eat German bread!
Can I get you a refill?
お代わりはどうですか？
I'll take one.
もらう！
Me, too.
私も
Thank you for that.
Your coffee was delicious.
ごちそうさま　コーヒーおいしかったわ
I'm glad. Please come again, okay?
よかった！
また来てくださいね
Mm-hmm, I'll be back for more.
うん　また飲みにくる
Hmm? Is something the matter?
どうしたんですか？
It's nothing. Thank you for the coffee.
なんでもない　ごちそうさま
Well, see you later.
じゃ　またね
Be sure to come by again, okay?
絶対　また来てくださいね～
冬支度　いいかげん何か見つけないと
We need to find some way
to get ready for winter, already.
I don't think it's going to be that easy
finding something better than these.
これ以上のものは　そう簡単に見つからないと思うけど
"Clothing, Appliances, Handbags"
"Sell yours here"
Do you remember what
we're here looking for?
何を探しにきたかわかってるの？
I can never settle for anything that
isn't the best there is for myself.
私は私にとって　常に最高で一番のものじゃないと納得いかないの
Whenever I come across
something like that,
そういうものと出会ったときは
it always leaps into my field of vision
and speaks to me, saying,
いつも向こうからこっちの視界に飛び込んできて
私を連れて帰って～って語りかけてくるんだから
"Take me home with you!"
Mm-hmm, okay.
フーン　そう
Ah, a Trangia mess tin.
It's like a miniature mess kit.
あぁ　トランギアのメスティンね
小型の飯ごうで　ごはんを炊くだけじゃなくて
It not only cooks rice, you can also boil,
steam, grill, and deep fry with it.
煮物　焼き物　蒸し物にオイル缶　万能の調理器具よ
It's a do-everything cooking utensil.
Okay then, what's it gonna be?
ほらほら　どうするの？
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございました～
Koguma-san, do you remember
what we're here looking for?
小熊さ～ん　何を探しにきたかわかってるの～？
I came to buy this bento box.
I just decided.
私はこの弁当箱を買いにきた
今そう決めた
What should we do? Go check out
Up Garage, just to be sure?
どうする？念のため　UP GARAGE のほうも見ておく？
Hmm, but we just barely went there.
う～ん　でもこの前行ったばっかりだし
Give me your smartphone.
スマホ貸して
What? What is it?
なに？どうしたの？
Handlebar covers.
ハンドルカバー
Huh?
はっ？
Yeah, handlebar covers.
そう　ハンドルカバー
冬に仕事でバイクに乗る人間には　これがいちばんいいって読んだことがある
I read somewhere that people
who have to ride motorbikes for work
during the winter say they're the best.
軍手を変えるのが嫌なら
If you don't want to change
your work gloves,
then you can cover your handle
grips themselves with them.
ハンドルグリップそのものをこれで覆えばいい
Huh? No way! They're so uncool!
え～っ　やだ　カッコ悪い！
A Cub with handlebar covers
looks like an old fogey's Cub!
カブにハンカバなんて　おじいちゃんのカブじゃない！
There's no way I'm putting
them on my Hunter Cub.
私のハンターカブには絶対つけないからね！
I'm buying some.
These are within my price range.
私は買う　これなら値段も手が届く
Good.
よし
Ugh.
ゲッ
"Purchase"
Welcome!
いらっしゃいませ！
礼子ちゃん　小熊さん！来てくれたんだ！
Reiko-chan! Koguma-san! You stopped by!
Ah, welcome.
あぁ　いらっしゃい
Hello.
どうも
With those handlebar covers,
my work gloves are good enough.
ハンドルカバーがあれば　軍手で十分ね～
手の周りに無風の空間を作る
They create a windbreak around our hands.
It's such a simple design,
but more effective than I imagined.
単純な構造だけど　こんなにも効果的とはね
The wind doesn't come up
our jacket sleeves.
上着の袖から風が入ってこない
That helps alleviate the cold
on our upper bodies.
上半身の寒さまで少し和らいだ
防寒とはすなわち防風ってことね
So cold-proofing is really more
like wind-proofing, isn't it?
Then again, I'm sure it won't be enough.
けど　きっとまだ足りない
まっ　まずは第一段階突破ってことで
Well, here's to clearing
the first phase, anyhow.
Shii-chan, can I get a refill?
椎ちゃ～ん　お代わり！
Shii-chan?
椎ちゃ～ん
Huh? Oh...
えっ？あぁ
I'm sorry. Listen, maybe
you should get going now.
ごめんなさい　あの…
そろそろ帰ってもらったほうがいいかも
Huh?
え～っ？
This is about the time when we get
a lot of customers coming in.
これからお客さん結構混む時間なんです
I really am sorry.
ホントにごめんなさい
Oh, I see.
そうなんだ
Just a moment.
待ってくれ！
I'd like you both to sample
my landbrot before you go.
お二人にはこれから　私のラントブロートを試食してもらいたいんだ
"Landbrot"? Isn't that the rye bread
that German soldiers choked down?
ラントブロートって　ドイツの兵隊がマズそうに食べてた黒パン？
兵隊パンのコミスブロートより　こっちのほうが食べやすい
This is much more palatable than
the komisbrot the soldiers had.
I'll have some!
食べる！
But this is when we get
swarmed with customers!
お客さんいっぱい来ちゃうころだよ!?
Huh? I'm sure we'll be fine.
えっ？まだ大丈夫だよ
も～っ　だめだって！
Oh, I'm telling you, no!
Okay, well...
それじゃ…
Now, now, where's the harm,
where's the harm?
まぁまぁ！いいじゃない　いいじゃない！
I'll try some of that rye bread.
黒パンいただきま～す
That's more like it.
そうこなくっちゃ
パパ！も～っ　礼子ちゃん！
Papa!
Oh, Reiko-chan!
If it gets crowded,
we'll leave right away.
混んできたらすぐ帰るって
Unless... there's some other reason
you're trying to chase us out of here?
それとも　すぐに追い出したい理由でもあるっていうの？
No, not particularly...
そんなの別に…
I'm home!
ただいま～
Welcome back.
おかえり
Shii's friends are here.
椎の友達が来てるんだよ
友達？
Friends?
Oh, Reiko-san, nice to see you.
あらぁ　礼子さん　いらっしゃい
Hello.
どうも
And also, look, it's Koguma-san,
from the culture festival.
それと　ほら　文化祭の小熊さん
えっ
Huh? Oh!
あらぁ！
あなたが！娘から話は聞いてるわ
You're the one? My daughter has
told me so much about you!
It's a pleasure to meet you, Koguma-san.
はじめまして　小熊さん
I'm Shii's mother.
椎の母です
Hello...
どうも…
Ooh, I've been hoping to meet you!
会いたかったわぁ
Here you go.
は～い　どうぞ
Koguma-san?
小熊さんは？
I'm fine.
大丈夫です
お代わり　いつでも言ってね
If you need a refill, just let me know.
Oh, thank you.
はぁ… どうも
A father who's obsessed with Germany
and an America-loving mother...
ドイツに憧れる父親と　アメリカ好きの母親か
The transition in the floor there
is like the Atlantic Ocean.
あの床の境目が大西洋ってとこね
The sandwich counter is British, right?
サンドイッチ売り場はイギリスなんでしょ？
That's probably a middle ground
that the two compromised on.
そこは 2 人が折り合った　折衷案ってところじゃない？
Hmm...
イタリア… ちっちゃ
And a tiny sliver of Italy.
It might be fun to come by
and see just how big it becomes.
どれだけ大きくなるか　見にくるのも悪くない… か
Well, as long as she's riding
a British-made Moulton,
まっ　イギリス製のモールトンに乗ってるうちは　まだまだね
there's plenty of room.
You look different than in the
classroom when you're wearing that.
それがあると　教室と違って見える
えっ？
Huh? Oh...
Please come by again, okay?
また来てください
Mm-hmm.
うん
礼子ちゃんも
Reiko-chan, you, too.
I'll stop by in the morning. Until then.
また朝寄るから　よろしく
Mm-hmm.
うん！
秋の終わりを感じていた
We were feeling the tail end of autumn.
Our handlebar covers were outstanding,
ハンドルカバーは優秀だけど
but we'll need some more basic
cold-weather measures going forward.
これから先　もっと本格的な防寒対策が必要になる
家でも作れるコーヒーで　ガソリン満タン 1 回分のお金を取る
I figured that there was no
future in getting café coffee
when I can make it at home and
it costs as much as a full tank of gas.
カフェなんてものは　縁がないと思っていた
でも　それはふだんの話
But that is typically speaking.
Supposing I wanted to
indulge myself a little,
例えば　ちょっと贅沢をしたくなったり
and absolutely have to have
a cup to warm myself up...
体を温める一杯がどうしても欲しくなったときには
...it wouldn't be such a bad thing
to stop by that shop... would it?
あの店に立ち寄ってみるのも悪くない… かな
すれ違う風　未来に溶けてく
近づいてくる　優しいエンジンの音
透明だった世界に　車輪で色を付けよう
ともに駆け抜けた道
誰にも描けない私の絵になる
遠くで春が呼ぶ　すぐそこかもしれない
できるだけたくさんの　思い出連れてこう
一緒に過ごす日々　見つけた彩りは決して
色褪せない
いつだってずっと　そばにいるよ
"In Ice"
"Super Cub Episode 9"
Episode 9: "In Ice."
第 9 話　「氷の中」